<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../src-generated/schemas/fhir-single.xsd">
  <blockquote class="stu-note">
    <p>
      This implementation guide is not fully complete.  Portions of the implementation guide are provided for "framework purposes only" - giving a sense of what additional topics are intended to be covered and where that content will fit.  The work group has prioritized standardizing those portions of the specification with general applicability.  The work group will continue to flesh out additional sections for future ballot publications.
    </p>
  </blockquote>
  <a name="scope"> </a>
  <h2>Scope</h2>
  <p>The scope of this implementation guide is to describe how HCBS data requirements, documented in the 56 data elements included in the eLTSS Dataset, can be represented for exchange and sharing using FHIR.</p>
<p>The IG will use FHIR US Core R4 as a starting point and will profile the following resources as necessary to enable eLTSS Plan Creation and Exchange: </p>
<ul>
<li>CarePlan</li> 
<li>CareTeam</li> 
<li>Goal </li>
<li>Location </li>
<li>Observation </li>
<li>Organization </li>
<li>Patient </li>
<li>Practitioner </li>
<li>Questionnaire </li>
<li>QuestionnaireResponse </li>
<li>Related Person </li>
<li>RiskAssesment </li>
<li>ServiceRequest</li>
</ul>


<H2>1.4	 US Core Dependency</H2>
<p>Please note that implementations using this eLTSS FHIR IG must comply with US Core when applicable. US Core defines the minimum conformance requirements for accessing patient data as defined by the Argonaut pilot implementations and the ONC 2015 Edition Common Clinical Data Set (CCDS). These profiles are intended to be the foundation for US Realm FHIR implementation guides. Therefore, US Core Profiles, US Core Terminology,  US Core Capability Statements / Conformance Requirements, and Security Considerations not specifically noted in this guide must be included when applicable.</p>
</div>