<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../src-generated/schemas/fhir-single.xsd">


<div class="stu-note">

  <!--h4 id="plain-language-summary">Plain Language Summary about HL7 and this Guide<a class="anchorjs-link " href="#plain-language-summary" aria-label="Anchor" data-anchorjs-icon="" style="font: 1em / 1 anchorjs-icons; padding-left: 0.375em;"></a></h4-->

  <p>Changes to look out for:</p>

  <ul>
    <li>Deprecation of CarePlan.activity.detail, reduces opportunity for variability in delivery of data elements</li>
    <li>Recommendations on use of Task and the <a href="implementation.html#resource-pertainstogoal-extension">extension:resource-pertainstogoal</a></li>
	<li>Clarification on occurrenceTiming</li>
	<li>See, <a href="eLTSS_to_FHIR_R4_element.html">changes to Mapping eLTSS to FHIR</a>, <a href="StructureDefinition-ServiceRequest-eltss.html">ServiceRequest.occurrence[x]</a>, <a href="implementation.html">Implementation topics</a>, <a href="StructureDefinition-CarePlan-eltss.html">CarePlan removal of CarePlan.activity.detail</a></li>
	<li>USCORE version is 3.1.1</li>
	<li>Add <a href="eLTSS_to_FHIR_R4_element.html#units">non-ucum coded units and ucum units</a> as examples for use in quantities</li>
	<li>Removed US CORE mapping page as the data is now redundant through Profiling of USCORE Profiles</li>
	<li>Added <a href="https://build.fhir.org/ig/HL7/eLTSS/branches/master/implementation.html#task-used-with-servicerequest">Task Guidance on Implementation topics page</a> and <a href="artifacts.html#other">examples</a> of Task</li>
	<li>Added simulated example of CarePlan and associated artifacts to aid implementers <a href="artifacts.html#example-example-instances">here</a> and <a href="artifacts.html#other">here</a></li>
	<li>Added page on <a href="testing.html">Testing</a>	</li>
	<li>Added draft for new <a href="OperationDefinition-all-eltss-careplan.html">FHIR Operation</a> for retrieving all eLTSS data associated with a CarePlan</li>
	<li>Enhanced server capability statement to make the expectations more clear <a href="CapabilityStatement-eltss-client.html">eLTSS USCORE Capability Statement</a></li>
	<li>Increased clarity of FHIR data elements to support for eLTSS data exchange through additional Must Support (MS) in <a href="profiles.html">all Profiles</a></li>
	<li>Extended guidance with new profiles for <a href="StructureDefinition-PractitionerRole-eltss.html">PractitionerRole</a>, <a href="StructureDefinition-QuestionnaireResponse-eltss.html">QuestionnaireResponse</a> and <a href="StructureDefinition-RelatedPerson-eltss.html">RelatedPerson</a></li>
	<li><a href="StructureDefinition-Condition-eltss.html">Condition category</a> now using "Health Concern" from USCORE</li>
	<li>eLTSS Observation <a href="ValueSet-eltss-observation-code.html">value set for Preference and Strength</a> now using LOINC code for "Care experience Preference"</li>	
	<li>
		<p>Please review and comment</p>
		<!--ul>
			<li>Should we constrain ServiceRequest.occurrence to ONLY allow occurenceTiming in the IG?</li>
			<li>Familiarity with HL7 projects such as <a href="https://www.hl7.org/about/davinci/">Da Vinci Project</a></li>
			<li>Do any of the changes break your current implementation?</li>
			<li>Do any of the changes improve your current implementation or planning?</li>
			<li>Additional implementation concerns?</li>
		</ul-->
	</li>
  </ul>
</div>

  <h3>Introduction to the Guide</h3><a name="introduction"> </a>
<p><!--Updated the first sentence and 2 other areas to specify US Core 3.0 for #28236-->
The electronic Long-Term Services and Supports (eLTSS) Implementation Guide (IG) is based on <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/R4/index.html">FHIR R4</a> and <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/us/core/STU3.1.1/index.html">US Core v3.1.1</a>. It was developed to support exchange of data generated during the planning and provision of long-term services and supports and is currently scoped to data commonly found on LTSS service plans.
</p>

<p>
It is expected that the readers of this guide are familiar with the eLTSS use case, FHIR R4 and USCORE. To become familiar with the eLTSS use case, please refer to the ONC documentation of the use case, found here <a href="https://oncprojectracking.healthit.gov/wiki/display/TechLabSC/eLTSS+Use+Case+Development+and+Functional+Requirements">https://oncprojectracking.healthit.gov/wiki/display/TechLabSC/eLTSS+Use+Case+Development+and+Functional+Requirements</a>. Additionally, an HL7 Domain Analysis Model (DAM), which defines data elements important to eLTSS data transmission, can be found here <a href="http://www.hl7.org/implement/standards/product_brief.cfm?product_id=495">“HL7 Cross-Paradigm Information Sharing for Electronic Long-Term Services and Supports (eLTSS), Release 1”</a>. 
Please note, this implementation guide attempts to inform how to package eLTSS data elements for exchange between systems. This guide provides implementation guidance for eLTSS data elements, including communicating patient participation in care. The guidance is found as a mixture of mapping guidance, narration, example, testing recommendation, and FHIR artifacts. FHIR R4 Core and USCORE provide a rich resource of detail to support the base FHIR implementation that this IG assumes. To successfully implement an eLTSS solution in FHIR, implementers should become familiar with both. Access to FHIR R4 Core and USCORE guidance can be found where relevant through the artifacts of this guide. For instance, when reviewing profiles, please be sure to view the Snapshot Table on the FHIR profiles, as well as the Differential Table, and note the links to the guidance on the artifact from which the profile is derived.
</p>

  <h3>Background on eLTSS</h3><a name="background"> </a>
<p><!--Updated the first sentence and 2 other areas to specify US Core 3.0 for #28236-->
The electronic Long-Term Services and Supports (eLTSS) Implementation Guide (IG) is based on <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/R4/index.html">FHIR R4</a> and <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/us/core/STU3.1.1/index.html">US Core v3.1.1</a>. It was developed to support exchange of data generated during the planning and provision of long-term services and supports and is currently scoped to data commonly found on LTSS service plans.
</p>
  <p>
  Long-term services and supports (LTSS) are needed by millions of people, including children, adults and individuals over age 65, due to various disabling conditions and chronic illnesses. Long-term services are comprised of a diverse set of assistances designed to help with general care, activities of daily living (ADLs), and instrumental activities of daily living (IADLs) like eating, toileting, dressing, cooking, driving, managing money, etc. These services are provided across various settings from facility-based or institutional care to community-based settings. Services and supports provided in the person’s home or in a community setting are referred to as Community-Based Long-Term Services and Supports (CB-LTSS) or Home and Community-Based Services (HCBS).
  </p>
  <p>
  The eLTSS data is currently and primarily used by LTSS service providers and care managers and resides in case management systems and LTSS provider systems. This IG is designed to streamline the ability to exchange and make this data available to all members participating in the care of the beneficiary (patient) including clinical and non-clinical care providers as well as the beneficiary and their representative(s). 
  </p>
  <p>
The eLTSS data referenced in this implementation guide refers to the eLTSS Dataset that was developed by the eLTSS Initiative, a joint project between the Office of the National Coordinator for Health Information Technology (ONC) and the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services (CMS). The eLTSS Dataset was input for the Informative Document titled <a href="http://www.hl7.org/implement/standards/product_brief.cfm?product_id=495">“HL7 Cross-Paradigm Information Sharing for Electronic Long-Term Services and Supports (eLTSS), Release 1”</a> balloted during the September 2018 cycle. This IG further advances the eLTSS Dataset to FHIR mapping found in the Informative Document to provide FHIR-specific implementer guidance.  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <a href="background.html">Project Background</a> and the <a href="usecases.html">eLTSS Use Cases</a> included in this Guide.
</p>

  <a name="scope"> </a>
  <h3>Scope</h3>
  <p>The scope of this implementation guide is to describe how LTSS (also referred to as Home and Community-Based Service (HCBS)) data requirements, documented in the 56 data elements included in the eLTSS Dataset, can be represented for exchange and sharing using FHIR.</p>
  <p>
The concept of an eLTSS service plan most closely aligns with the FHIR CarePlan resource, which is semantically a good fit. The diagram below shows the FHIR resources utilized in the mapping as well as the FHIR data elements used to link these resources. Parentheses indicates the eLTSS Dataset data element (e.g. Assessed Need, Preference) or group of elements (e.g. Beneficiary Demographics, Person Indicators). Lines indicate linkages between FHIR resources and are labeled with the FHIR data element that provides the reference.</p>
  <!--img src="CarePlan_FHIR_mapping_centered_narrow.png"/-->
  <img src="eLTSS_FHIRresourceView.png"/>
  <br/>
  <br/>
  <p>The IG will use <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/R4/index.html">FHIR R4</a>, and <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/us/core/STU3.1.1/index.html">US Core v3.1.1</a> as a starting point and will profile resources as necessary to enable eLTSS Plan Creation and Exchange. Please refer to <a href="profiles.html">eLTSS FHIR Profiles</a> for additional details.</p>
  <p> For a detailed view of how eLTSS maps to FHIR R4, please refer to the <a href="eLTSS_to_FHIR_R4_element.html">eLTSS Dataset to FHIR Release 4 Mapping</a> included in this guide.</p>
  
  
  <a name="us-core"/>
  <h3>US Core Dependency</h3>
  <p>Please note that implementations using this eLTSS FHIR IG must comply with <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/us/core/STU3.1.1/index.html">US Core v3.1.1</a> when applicable. US Core defines the minimum conformance requirements for accessing patient data as defined by the Argonaut pilot implementations and the ONC 2015 Edition Common Clinical Data Set (CCDS). These profiles are intended to be the foundation for US Realm FHIR implementation guides. Therefore, <a href="http://www.hl7.org/fhir/us/core/#us-core-profiles">US Core Profiles</a>, <a href="http://www.hl7.org/fhir/us/core/STU3.1.1/terminology.html">US Core Terminology</a>,  <a href="http://www.hl7.org/fhir/us/core/STU3.1.1/capstmnts.html">US Core Capability Statements / Conformance Requirements</a>, and <a href="http://www.hl7.org/fhir/us/core/STU3.1.1/security.html">Security Considerations</a> not specifically noted in this guide must be included when applicable.</p>
  
  <a name="actors"/>
  <h3>eLTSS Actors</h3>
  <p>The eLTSS Informative Document identified four actors who may be involved in the exchange of service plans. The list below outlines these actors and a brief description of their role in LTSS:</p>
  <ul>
    <li><b>Beneficiary (Patient/Care Recipient):</b> Individual who is eligible for and receives LTSS. Also, referred to as recipient, consumer, person, client, participant, and individual.</li>
    <li><b>Support Planner:</b> Individual who helps the patient/care recipient explore, understand options, and make appropriate choices among community resources and services; engages in person-centered planning and assists the care recipient with the creation, implementation and updating of a person-centered service plan.
This role is often referred to as case manager, care coordinator, etc.</li>
    <li><b>HCBS Provider:</b> A provider of an authorized service which assists in maintaining and enabling the care recipient to continue living in his or her home and community (e.g. social worker, in-home supportive service provider, direct-care worker/personal care aide, adult day care provider, multipurpose older adult service program provider, case manager, personal care provider, home care agency, hospice care agency, job development and supported employment, equipment and technology, peer specialist, community integration, support broker, fiscal intermediary, and others who provide assistance in support of participant direction, etc.).</li>
    <li><b>Clinical and Institutional-based Provider:</b> A provider of medical or health service and any other person or organization that furnishes, bills, or is paid for health care services in the normal course of business. This includes a licensed/certified and/or qualified person who provides health care, who is authorized to implement a portion of the plan and who has care responsibilities (e.g. physician, advanced practice nurse, physician assistant, nurse, nurse practitioner, nurse care manager, psychologist, therapist, pharmacist, dietician/nutritionist, specialist, dentist, emergency department provider, etc.). 
This also includes an organization including, but not limited to a hospital including short-term acute care hospital and specialty hospital (e.g., long-term care hospital, rehabilitation facility, and psychiatric hospital, etc.), ambulatory surgery center, provider practice, and nursing home.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>US Core defines two actors: </p>
  <ul>
    <li><b>US Core Requestor:</b> An application that initiates a data access request to retrieve patient/care recipient and service data. This can be thought of as the client in a client-server interaction.</li>
    <li><b>US Core Responder:</b> A product that responds to the data access request providing patient/care recipient and service data. This can be thought of as the server in a client-server interaction.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>The eLTSS actors correspond to the US Core requestor actor when an eLTSS plan is exchanged using FHIR.</p>
  
  
  <a name="how-to-read-this-guide"/>
  <h3>How to Read this guide</h3>
  <p>This Guide is divided into several pages, which can be found on the menu bar on the top of each page</p>
  
  
  <p>
The guide contains a mapping page for eLTSS elements mapped into FHIR R4. This page is a very important page. eLTSS requires very few constraints beyond US CORE 3.1.1 on core FHIR R4, thus the profiles are largely for convenience. There are a few Must Supports not included in US CORE 3.1.1 and some Resources which are not covered by US CORE 3.1.1, so the FHIR profiles are still needed. However, the mapping page is a summation of where eLTSS data elements should be placed/found in FHIR.  
</p>


  <ul>
  <li><a href="index.html" >IG Home</a>: Provides the introduction and background.</li>
  <li><a href="implementation.html">Implementation Considerations</a>: This page provides considerations for implementing eLTSS using FHIR, including other Implementation Guides, Task and ClaimResource</li>
  
  <!--li><a href="index.html" title="IG Home">Conformance</a>: Recommendations on testing.</li-->
  <li><a href="index.html" >Mapping</a>: Provides implementers with the location of FHIR fields where eLTSS data elements should be found.
  <ul><li><a href="eLTSS_to_FHIR_R4_element.html"></a>:Guidance for eLTSS elements in FHIR R4.</li></ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="testing.html">Testing</a>: Provides pointers on testing</li>
  
  <li>Artifacts: FHIR artifacts can be found here
  <ul>
	<li><a href="profiles.html">Profiles</a>: FHIR profiles contain machine readable constraints on the FHIR specification. The narrative sections are important to review as well.</li>
	<li><a href="examples.html">Examples</a>: Look here for examples to guide your implementation.</li>
	<li><a href="extensions.html">Extensions</a>: Extensions provide specific additional data elements not found in the core specification.</li>
	<li><a href="OperationDefinition-all-eltss-careplan.html">All-eLTSS retrieval Operation</a>: The Operation is an extension of the FHIR search specification for returning all data associated with an eLTSS CarePlan.</li>
	<li><a href="capabilities.html">Capability Statements</a>: Capability statements describe the capabilities of systems implementing the IG.</li>
	<li><a href="vocabulary.html">Value Sets</a>: This page contains the value sets created for the IG. The value sets provide coded terms for use with specific data elements.</li>
  </ul>
  </li>
  
  
  <!--li><a href="guidance.html">Guidance</a>: The Guidance pages document best practices and how to use the profiles and transactions defined in this guide.
    <ul>
      <li><a href="uscdi.html">USCDI</a>: This page maps the US Core Profiles to the (USCDI) data classes and data elements.</li>
      <li><a href="general-guidance.html" title="General Guidance Page">General Guidance</a>: This page provides guidance and definitions and requirements common to all actors and profiles used in this guide.</li>
      <li><a href="clinical-notes.html">Clinical Notes</a>: This page gives guidance on the interactions between Consumers and Producers of clinical notes.</li>
      <li><a href="medication-list.html">Medication List</a>: This page gives guidance on how a patient or provider can access a patient’s medications.</li>
      <li><a href="basic-provenance.html">Basic Provenance</a>: This page provides implementers with important definitions to create and share the Provenance Resource.</li>
      <li><a href="screening-and-assessments.html">Screening and Assessments</a>: This page documents how US Core Profiles are used to represent screenings and assessments for patient health status</li>
      <li><a href="changes-between-versions.html">Changes Between Versions</a>: This page considers the user and developer experience when transitioning between versions of US Core and documents the changes between versions.</li>
      <li><a href="future-of-US-core.html">Future of US Core</a>: This page outlines the approach to adding new content to US Core.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="artifacts.html">FHIR Artifacts</a>: These pages provide detailed descriptions and formal definitions for all the FHIR objects defined in this guide.
    <ul>
      <li><a href="profiles-and-extensions.html">Profiles and Extensions</a>: This page lists the US Core Profiles and Extensions defined in this guide to exchange quality data.
        <ul>
          <li>Each US Core Profile page includes a narrative description that lists all the <a href="must-support.html">Mandatory</a> and <a href="must-support.html">Must Support</a> data elements, profile-specific implementation guidance, and formal definition. A “Quick Start” guide summarizes the supported search transactions for each profile. Although the guidance typically focuses on the profiled elements, it also may cover un-profiled elements to aid with implementation and certification.</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li><a href="search-parameters-and-operations.html">Search Parameters and Operations</a>: This page lists the defined US Core Operations and Search Parameters used in US Core transactions.</li>
      <li><a href="terminology.html" title="Terminology Page">Terminology</a>: This page lists the US Core ValueSets, and CodeSystems defined for the profiles.</li>
      <li><a href="capability-statements.html">Capability Statements</a>: These pages define the expected FHIR capabilities of the US Core Servers and Clients.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="security.html">Security</a>: This page documents the general security requirements and recommendations for actors.</li>
  <li><a href="examples.html">Examples</a>: This page lists all the examples used in this guide. These example instances show what data produced and consumed by systems conforming with this implementation guide might look like. Every effort has been made to ensure that the examples are correct and useful, but they are not a normative part of the specification nor are they fully representative of real world examples.</li>
  <li><a href="downloads.html" title="Downloads Page">Downloads</a>: This page provides links to downloadable artifacts.</li>
  <li><a href="changes.html">Change Log</a>: This page documents the changes across the versions of US Core</li-->
</ul>
  
  <a name="Credits and Authors"/>
  <h3>Credits and Authors</h3>
  <table Border="1">
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th>Name</th>
        <th>Role</th>
        <th>Organization</th>
	<th>Email</th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <td>Bret Heale</td>
        <td>STU2 IG developer</td>
        <td>ELIMU and Humanized Health Consulting</td>
	<td>bheale@elimu.io</td>
      </tr>
      <!--tr>
        <td>Amber Patel</td>
        <td>Author</td>
        <td>Security Risk Solutions</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Anastasia Perchem</td>
        <td>Contributor</td>
        <td>Office of the National Coordinator for Health Information Technology</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Becky Angeles</td>
        <td>Author</td>
        <td>Carradora Health, Inc.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Bonnie Young</td>
        <td>Contributor</td>
        <td>Georgia Department of Community Health</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>David Pyke</td>
        <td>Author</td>
        <td>Ready Computing</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Elizabeth Palena-Hall</td>
        <td>Contributor</td>
        <td>Office of the National Coordinator for Health Information Technology</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Greg White</td>
        <td>Author</td>
        <td>Security Risk Solutions</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Irina Connelly</td>
        <td>Author</td>
        <td>Georgia Tech Research Institute</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Jack Wallace</td>
        <td>Author</td>
        <td>Georgia Tech Research Institute</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Jamie Parker</td>
        <td>Author</td>
        <td>Carradora Health, Inc.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>John Moehrke</td>
        <td>Author</td>
        <td>By Light Professional IT Services</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Johnathan Coleman</td>
        <td>Author</td>
        <td>Security Risk Solutions</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Kerry Lida</td>
        <td>Contributor</td>
        <td>Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Mark Meadows</td>
        <td>Contributor</td>
        <td>Georgia Department of Community Health</td>
      </tr-->
    </tbody>
  </table>
</div>
